那么让我们继续讲这个批渲染部分吧
so let's continue this batch rendering party
上次我们看了批渲染实际上是什么，我们说了一点理论
last time we took a look at what batch rendering actually was, we did a bit of theory
以及举了一个渲染两个正方形的简单的例子
and put together a basic example of just rendering two squares
如果你们错过了，就去看看那个视频，今天我们将继续
check out that video, if you missed it, and today we're gonna continue on
填补传统渲染的空白
with kind of filling in the blanks of what we could do with traditional rendering
那是批渲染做不到的
which we can't do with batch rendering
我想把所有这些特性都放进去
and kind of bringing all of those features I guess back into it
上次我们绘制了两个白色的四边形，也就是白色的方块
so last time we did just draw two white quads, two white squares
那很好，但最终你们可能会想做其他事情
and that was fine, obviously but eventually you're probably gonna want to do other things
例如，绘制不同颜色的四边形或绘制有纹理的四边形
for example, drawer quads of different colors or draw textured quads
或者动态地改变已经绘制出来的四边形
or dynamically changed the quads that are being drawn
所有这些东西，那正是这个迷你系列的主题
all those things and that's exactly what this mini series is about
我们会一步一步地讲解，用一种非常简单的方法把它分解
we're kind of going through everything step by step, breaking it down doing it in a really kind of simple way
然后填充所有我们想要用批渲染实现的东西
and then filling in everything that we would want to actually achieve with batch rendering
所以今天讲的都是颜色，我们如何绘制两个不同颜色的四边形
so today that's going to be all about color, how do we draw two quads of different colors
或者是任意数量的不同颜色的四边形
or in fact any number of quads with different colors
当我们想画一个有颜色的四边形时，如果你们想用最简单的方法
traditionally, when we want to draw a colored quad, if you think about the most simplest way
我的意思是最简单的方法可能很主观，对我来说可能很简单
I mean the simplest way is probably quite subjective, something that might be simple to me
可能对你们来说并不简单，你们可能认为其他方法很简单
might not be simple to you, you might think something else is simple
但是当我想到，让我们渲染一个四边形，一个有颜色的四边形
but when I think of like, let's just render a quad, a colored quad
用最基本的方式绘制一个扁平的彩色四边形我认为这很简单
a flat colored quad in the most basic way possible, what I think of is simply
用顶点位置填充顶点缓冲区，然后渲染那个四边形
filling in a vertex buffer with the vertex positions, and then rendering that quad
然后在片段着色器中
and then in the fragment shader
传入一个包含颜色的统一变量
passing in some kind of uniform variable which contains the color
当然，我们可以硬编码片段着色器为一个特定的颜色
of course we could just hard code the fragment shader to be a particular color
但如果我们有两个不同的四边形，那就没用了
but that wouldn't really be useful, if we have two different quads
我们得写两种不同的颜色，像这样而不是那样
we'd have to write two different shade or something, like that instead of that
我们要做的就是使用两个不同的绘制调用来渲染我们的正方形两次
what we would do is just render our quad twice using two different draw calls
然后在我们的片段着色器中有一个像vec4或vec3 color
but then have a uniform like vec4 or vec3 color inside our fragment shader
那里就是我们设置输出颜色的地方
which we would set the output color to be
那实际上会在绘制调用发生之前设置好
and then that would actually be kind of set up before the draw call happens
所以我可以用glUniform3f或glUniform4f
so I can just use like glUniform3f or glUniform4f
在绘制我的四边形之前设置这些变量，在调用glDrawElements之前
and actually set those variables before drawing my quad, before actually calling glDrawElements
那对我来说是绘制一个四边形最简单的方法
that's kind of to me what would be the simplest way of rendering a quad
但是我们不能再那样做了，而我们不能再那样做的原因是
however we can't do that anymore, and the reason we can't do that anymore is
因为我们只有一个DrawCall
because we just have one DrawCall
我们不能调用glUniform4f，然后调用glDrawElements
we can't call glUniform4f, then glDrawElements
然后再次调用glUniform4f，然后调用glDrawElements
and then call glUniform4f again, and then DrawElements
因为我们只有一个绘制元素调用，只有一个DrawElements调用
because we only have one elements call, we only have one DrawElements call
所以我们不能将统一变量设置为绘制之间的两个不同值
so we can't set the uniform to be two different values between drawers
怎么做呢，我们现在确实有很多实现这个的解决方法
what we do, now there are a number of solutions to this
我的意思是，你们可以有一个颜色值的数组
I mean you could have like an array of color values
你们可以传入索引，有很多不同你们可以做的东西
and you could kind of pass in the index, and like there's a lot of different things you could do
其中一些可能比另一些好
some of them better than others
但这个视频中我们解决这个要用的方法，我认为可能是
but the way that we're gonna solve it in this video is what I think is probably
最好的解决方法，我的意思是，当然只是主观的
the best way to solve it, I mean, subjectively of course
只是我的意见，没必要生气
just my opinion, no need to get mad
并且那就是通过使用顶点颜色，现在你们可能听说过顶点颜色
and that is by using vertex colors, now you may have heard of vertex colors before
那么我们来讨论一下，那到底意味着什么
so let's just talk a little bit about, what that actually means
目前我们的顶点只简单地包含一个位置
currently our vertex simply contains a position
所以每个顶点都有三个浮点数xyz，它定义了顶点的位置
so every vertex just has three floats xyz, and that defines the position of that vertex
但是位置并不是顶点能够包含的唯一内容，事实上
but positions are not the only things that vertices are capable of containing, and in fact
顶点和顶点位置经常互换使用，这是不太恰当的
the vertex and vertex position is often used interchangeably, which isn't exactly correct
例如，某人可能会引用对象的顶点
for example, someone might refer to the vertices of an object
实际上是在讨论一个对象的顶点位置
and really be talking about the vertex positions of an object
然而，顶点这个词以及它在图形编程中的实际含义只是一个点
however the word vertex and what it actually means in graphics programming is simply a point
它可以包含你们真正想要的所有数据
which can contain as much data as you really want it to do
你们可以在顶点中存储任何东西，然后在顶点着色器中访问这些数据
you could store absolutely anything inside of vertex, and then access that data inside your vertex shader
所以那就是我们今天要做的
so that's what we're going to do today
每个单独的顶点在我们的顶点缓存区中都会包含一个颜色
every single vertex that we actually have inside our vertex buffer is going to contain a color
然后我们会在顶点着色器顶点缓冲区中访问这个颜色
and then we're going to access that color from within the vertex buffer inside our vertex shader
然后传到片段着色器
pass it to the fragment shader
并且然后将它设置为输出颜色，因为现在每个顶点都包含一种颜色
and then set that as our output color, so since each vertex now contains a color
显然，每个坐标都可以是我们设置的任何颜色
obviously every coord has the ability to be any color we set it to
并且事实上，它的纹理更细，我们可以控制每个顶点的颜色
and in fact it's even finer grain than that, we can actually control the color of every vertex
因此，如果我们想这样做的话，就可以创造出一个梯度或者类似的东西
thus creating like a gradient or something like that, if we would want to do that
仅仅依赖于顶点和片段着色器之间的插值
just relying on the interpolation between the vertex and the fragment shaders
但不管怎样，那是另一个故事，所以我们来深入了解下这个
but anyway, that's the story for another day, so to break this down
我们今天要做的就是打开顶点缓冲区，给每个顶点添加颜色
all we're going to do today is just open up our vertex buffer, and just add a color into every vertex
然后在着色器中访问它，把它设为输出颜色
and then access that inside our shader, and set that as our output color
就那么简单，没有必要把事情复杂化，让我们深入代码并看一看
it's as simple as that, there's no need to complicate things, let's dive into the code and take a look
那么现在我们有上期视频创建的这两个白色方块
so at the moment we have these two white squares from the previous video
让我们给它们一些颜色，来到这里的顶点缓冲区
let's give them some color, let's come over here to our vertex buffer
它目前只包含这两个正方形的顶点位置
which currently contains just the vertex positions of these two squares
让我们在这里加一些颜色，比如蓝色和黄色
and let's add some colors here, maybe like a blue and a yellow
那么对于第一个四边形，我们就用一个漂亮的蓝色
so for this first quad, let's make it a nice blue color
我们在这儿添加一些值，红绿蓝和alpha
we'll add the values here red green blue and alpha
现在这给了这个顶点的颜色，但因为我们想让整个四边形是一个纯色
now this gives us a color for this vertex, but since we want the entire quad to be one solid color
我们需要将这个颜色复制到构成正方形的四个顶点上
we'll need to copy this color across all of these four vertices which make up our square
现在我们来看第二个四边形，我们用漂亮的黄色
now let's come down here to our second quad, and we'll make it a nice yellow color
我会为构成第二个正方形的所有顶点添加粘贴值
I'll add in the grab values for all of the vertices which make up that second square
就那样，我们有了两个正方形
and that's it, we have our two squares
每个顶点的前三个浮点数是那个顶点的xyz位置
where the first three floats of each vertex are the xyz position of that vertex
然后每个顶点接下来的四个浮点数是RGBA颜色值
and then the next four floats of each vertex are the RGBA color values
就那样了，那就是所有的数据，来到下面这儿
and that's it, that's all about data, going down here
我唯一需要改变的是我们这里的顶点属性声明
the only thing I need to change is the vertex attribute declarations we have here
因为我们改变了顶点缓冲区的布局，我们在这里做的是
since we changed our vertex buffer layout, what we're doing here is
将第一个属性0作为位置，我们不想改变它
treating the first attribute attribute zero as the position, and we don't want to change that
但我们要做的是添加另一个属性，也就是索引1
but what we want to do is add another attribute, which is going to be index one
并且那将是我们的颜色，也是四个浮点数的RGBA
and that's going to be our color, it's going to be four floats RGBA
然后这儿另一个需要改变的是步幅
and then the other thing that changes here is the stride
步幅是一个完整顶点的字节数，那么这里每个顶点有7个浮点数
the stride is how many bytes a complete vertex is, so here we have seven floats per vertex
所以我们可以把这两个都改成7，最后这是这个属性的偏移量
so we can just change both of these to seven, and finally this is the offset of that attribute
从顶点的第四个浮点数开始
which starts at the fourth float of our vertex
那么这就是我们的顶点，这三个浮点数的大小是多少
so this is our vertex, what is the size of these three floats
三个浮点数是12个字节，所以我们可以直接写入12
three floats are 12 bytes, so we can just write in 12
并将其转换为const void指针
and cast it into a const void pointer
因为那就是接口需要的，就那样吧，那就是我们在C++这边所要做的
because that's what the api wants, and that's it, that's all we have to do C++ side
然后我们像往常一样渲染它，我们在顶点缓冲区中得到这些颜色
then we just render it as usual, we've got those colors in the vertex buffer
那么现在我们要做的是修改我们的着色器，让它使用这些顶点颜色
so now what we need to do is modify our shader, so that it will use these vertex colors
现在我们已经得到了这个layout(location = 0) in vec3 a_Position
at the moment we've just got this layout(location = 0) in vec3 a_Position
就是顶点的位置，我们需要的是另一个
which is the position of our vertex, and what we need is another one of these
但是在位置1，因为索引1是我们设置的属性
but at location one, because index one is what we set our attribute to be
这就是vec4 a_Color，颜色在顶点着色器中不是很有用
and this is going to be our vec4 color, now our color isn't very useful in a vertex shader
我们要做的是使用这个颜色来着色我们所有的像素
what we want to do is use this color to shader all of our pixels with
所以我们需要在片段着色器中使用它
so we need it in our fragment shader
我们要做的是创建这个输出颜色变量，我叫它v_Color v表示变化
the way we do that is create this output color variable, I'll call it v_Color, v for varying
这就是这些变量的名称，我们将它设置为a_Color，就像那样
which is what these variables use to be called, and we'll set it equal to a_Color just like that
然后在片段着色器中，我要取那个v_Color变量
and then inside the fragment shader, I'm going to take in that v_Color variable
然后我将我们的输出颜色设置为v_Color
and then I'll set our output color to be that v_Color
就是那样，现在让我们启动这个，看看我们得到了什么，好了
and that's it, now let's launch this and see what we get, and there we go
我们有漂亮的颜色，对着这些颜色的乌克兰粉丝大声喊出来
we have our beautiful colors, shout out to my Ukrainian fans here with these colors
但不管怎样，那就是我们为四边形设置不同颜色的方法
but anyway, that's what we do to set different colors for our quads
尽管它们被挤在一个绘制中
even though they're batched together into a single drawer
所以就像我提到的超级简单的东西
so yeah as I mentioned super simple stuff
顶点颜色不仅仅用于四边形或2D渲染
vertex colors are used not just for quads or 2D rendering
而且对于3D渲染来说，例如，我们不需要渲染一个带有纹理的3D模型
but also for 3D rendering, for example, we don't necessarily need to render a 3D model with a texture
如果我们只是想让3D模型是纯色的，或者不同的子模型，类似于子网格
if we just want that 3D model to be like a solid color, or different sub models kind of sub meshes
在那个模型中是不同的颜色之类的
within that model to be different colors or something like that
如果我们在做low poly风格的游戏
if we're going with something like a low poly style game
或者不需要纹理之类的东西
or something that just doesn't need textures and textures and stuff like that
一些只依赖于颜色的东西
something that can just rely on colors
所以顶点颜色肯定被广泛使用，不仅仅是为了渲染，记住这一点
so vertex colors are definitely widely used, not just for too rendering, keep that in mind
但在这种情况下，它们真的非常有用
but in this case, they're really really useful
它是一个非常简单快速的方法来设置每个四边形的颜色
and a very easy quick way to set up the color of each quad
如果我们处理的是批处理场景，比如批渲染
if we're dealing with like a batched kind of scenario, like we are with batch rendering
但不管怎样，我希望你们喜欢这个视频
but anyway, I hope you guys enjoyed this video
如果你们喜欢的话，就为它点赞吧
if you did, please hit that like button
并且也可以在下方留下你们的想法
and also leave a comment with your thoughts below
我也有一个patreon，也就是patreon.com/TheCherno
also I do have a patron, patreon.com/TheCherno
非常感谢所有在patreon上支持我的人
huge thank you to everyone who supports me on patreon
因为是你们让这些视频成为了可能
because you are what make these kinds of videos possible
下次我们将会说一说纹理，那么我们已经讲了颜色，那很好
next time we're going to be talking about textures, so we've covered colors and that's great
但如果我想让每个四边形都是不同的纹理呢
but what if I want each of my quads to be a different texture
那么也许渲染贴图，就需要水贴图和草贴图，也许渲染带有文本的标签
so maybe I'm rendering a tile map, and I need water tiles grass tiles, maybe I'm rendering a label with text
我需要每个四边形都是不同的字符，我该怎么做呢
and I need each quad to be a different character, how do I do all of that
我们如何处理一个批处理场景中的不同纹理
how do we deal with different textures inside a batched scenario
我们下次就会讨论那个，下次见，拜
we're going to talk about that next time, I will see you then, goodbye